Guide to the Society for the Relief of Half-Orphan and Destitue Children Records,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Society for the Relief of Half-Orphan and Destitue Children Records,
1836-1923
[Bulk Dates: 1853-1922]
Society for the Relief of Half-Orphan and Destitute Children in the City of New York.
1.47 linear ft. (3.5 document boxes).
Columbia University Rare Books and Manuscript Library, Butler Library, New York, NY 10027.
MS#1176
4079808
This collection is comprised of a register of childrens’ names and their backgrounds, agreements between the child's guardian and the Society, Executive Board minutes, application notes and lists of dismissed children.
Historical Note
The Society for the Relief of Half-Orphan and Destitute Children was established in 1835. Its purpose was to provide aid to single parents or relatives, most of whom were immigrants, for a weekly or monthly fee. It was incorporated by the New York State Legislature on April 27, 1837 and located in New York City at 67 West Tenth Street, near Sixth Avenue. The Society provided room, board and education to boys and girls from the ages of four through ten. In addition to the fees paid by the parents, the Society was financially supported by donations and funds from the government. From the mid-19th century to the early 20th century, the Society accepted and helped more than two thousand needy children.
Scope and Content
The records in this collection consist of a register of children and their background information, Executive Board meeting minutes, bound books of signed agreements between the parent and the Society, descriptive application notes of children and parents, and general correspondence.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in six series:
Series I: Register, 1836-1856
Series II: Agreement Books, 1872-1932
Series III: Executive Board Minutes, 1853-1922
Series IV: Applications Book, 1887-1920
Series V: Dismissal Book, 1847-1857
Series VI: Correspondence & Printed Material, 1880-1923
Subjects
Protestant Half Orphan Asylum (New York, N.Y.); Society for the Relief of Orphans (New York, N.Y.); Society for the Relief of Half-Orphan and Destitute Children in the City of New York; Charities--New York (State)--New York.; Children--Institutional Care--New York (State); Orphanages--New York (State)--New York.; Orphans--New York (State)--New York.; Lists.; Minutes.; Registers.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
School of Social Work Library Transfer Columbia University 03/07/89 M-89-03-07
Transferred from the School of Social Work Library, 1989.
Finding aid in repository; folder level control.
- Series I: Register, 1836-1856
  This series consists of a register book. The register includes childrens’ names, parents’ names, parents’ occupations, addresses and religious information.
  - Register of Childrens’ Names and Background Information, 1836-1856 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Series II: Agreement Books, 1872-1932
  This series is comprised of bound books of signed and dated agreements between the parent or relative giving custody to the Society of a child or children.
  - Agreement Books, 1872-1892 (3 Items) (Box 1, Folder 2 to 4)
  - Agreement Books, 1892-1932 (2 Items) (Box 2, Folder 1 to 2)
- Series III: Executive Board Minutes, 1853-1922
  This series consists of the monthly meeting reports of the Society.
  - Monthly Board Meetings’ Minutes, 1853-1875 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Monthly Board Meetings’ Minutes, 1895-1922 (3 Items) (Box 3, Folder 2 to 4)
- Series IV: Applications Book, 1887-1920
  In this series, handwritten notes have been recorded detailing the date, parent’s name, and child’s name with some background information.
  - Descriptive Applications of Parents and Children, 1887-1920 (Box 4)
- Series V: Dismissal Book, 1847-1857
  This series contains in a bound book, names of children who were discharged from the Society, either by their parents or relatives or by death.
  - Listings of Children Who Were Picked Up by Parent or Relative, 1847-1857 (Box 4)
- Series VI: Correspondence & Printed Materials, 1880-1923
  This series contains letters to the Society, blank donation slips and receipts, and other general items.
  - Letters to Board members and notes of appreciation, 1915-1919 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Blank donation slips and receipts, undated (Box 4)